Okay, so let me start firstly with, as usual, an intuition. So before I do that, let me just
give you a brief summary, or not a brief description of what that is about. So that, for example,
we want to prove, for example, how to prove properties, recursive functions on trees.
That's an example, because trees are the datatype example that we have done
until now. So the intuition, recall that for natural numbers, or not, let me just,
yeah, the same natural, I'll do it for natural numbers for now, but the same for lists.
For natural numbers to prove, maybe I'll do it for lists instead, because they are
datastructure, more similar in datastructure, but it's the same idea as natural numbers.
So recall that for lists, to prove that, to prove that a property p holds for all lists,
we did the following, or we needed, not we did the following, but we needed to prove two things,
or two goals, right? So the goal number zero, the base case, that is to say the property holds for
number zero, and goal number one, the step case, and that was to show that property holds,
sorry, that to show that the property holds for a list x's, then for arbitrary additional
element x property, we have that the property holds for x comes x's, so x added to x's.
So what did that mean? What that meant is that this, like roughly, this gives us algorithm,
not the two, like if you have the two theorems, the base case and the step case,
they give us an algorithm to show that property holds for any given list, like any given list,
for example, the list is called x1, like if this has x1, x2, comes xn, comes the empty list,
then we can show that the property given, can hold for this list, how? We can firstly show
step one, show, step zero, show the property, then using the using base case, and then step one,
show p of xn comes the empty list, using the step case, and then step two, it holds for xn
minus one, xn comes the empty list, again, using the step case, and then you can show it in
n steps, right? So show the property holds for x1, comes x2, comes xn, comes the empty list,
using the step case again. Okay, so what does that tell us? It tells us that mathematical induction
can, like, we use mathematical induction to get, to come up with proofs
for properties of algebraic datatypes, that the property holds for any
object or term of a certain algebraic datatype, and using this algorithm. So you prove the step
case and the base case, and this basically gives you an algorithm to show that the property holds
for anything that has the type list, for example, in our case, right? So it gives us this algorithm,
and crucially, it depends on the finiteness of the given element, or like a given type,
the elements of the given type, right? Every element has to be constructed using a finite number
of applications of cons, right? So now, the same was for initial numbers. Any number is a finite
application of suck, right? And then because of that, because of that, you can always
derive the property for any natural number, right? So now, let's go to trees, right?
So the intuition for trees. So how does that intuition transfer to trees?
Okay, so remember, we said that for lists, you can always use the base case to prove
that the property holds for the anti-list, and then you can go up one element at a time,
show that the property holds the list, which is extended by every element. So
every single element, you go through the list from the start of it, and then show that the property
holds here using the base case, and then you show that it holds for this list using the step case,
and then you show that it holds for this using the step case again, and using what you have shown
previously, and then so on and so forth. So you keep showing that it holds for more and more
of the list, right? So how would that translate to a tree? So a tree looks like that, right? So
for example, so you have, let me just show you, maybe let me just here draw that as the base,
so I'll just use that similar as the base. So here for a tree, it looks like that, right?
So a tree is like this, for example, a binary tree. That's an example binary tree. Okay,
so how would that translate? So if we want to move that intuition there to the binary tree,
what we would do is the following. We would have, we hope to prove, like our induction proof would
give us that the property holds for all the empty case, but so the base, sorry, like the base case
of the induction proof would give us that the property holds for all, for the, for the,
for the empty, for the, for the entry tree, right? For all the entities, like in the same way,
give it, give it to us here for, for the empty list. Do you want to give, do you want to have
that for the base case, from the base case? We want to have that the property holds from the
base case, from all of these base cases, and then the stat cases would allow us to combine
all, all components. Like, for example, would allow us to combine this,
that the property holds for that and that and then deduce that it holds for the whole tree.
And then the property holds for that and that, and then deduce that it holds for the whole,
this whole tree, and then that it, and then in order for you to show that it holds
for this tree, you need to show that first it holds for this base case and base case and then that
and then up, right? So you basically want to show that p holds here with the base case and base case
and with the base case, for example, and then use, okay, and then use the the holes for this base
case and then use the tools for this base case and that base case to show that it holds for
this tree using the step case, right? And then use the tools for this sub tree and that sub tree,
which is a leaf, to show that it holds for this tree again using the step case. And then
you chose that it holds for this base and this base, this with the base.
We need to do it a little bit more and then for this base and then show that it holds for this
tree using the step and then not only show that it holds for the whole tree, you have to repeat the
process for the right sub tree again and then let it and then show that that it holds for the whole
step, right? So that basically is the intuition of mathematical induction for trees. Like we want to
create, like we want to prove some things that give us an algorithm to prove that the property
holds for any given tree, right? So that is, how can we do that? So we have the first goal,
as I said, we need to prove it for all bases. So, goal zero, prove, goal zero, prove that property
holds any leaf and goal one, the property, prove that if we have the property any
tree one and tree two, so we have the property for T one and for T twos, then we can show
it holds for the tree constructed by adding the node X as parent to the two trees where X is
an arbitrary node, okay? So that's the intuition of proving things with mathematical induction
on trees, right? So you have that's the base case and that is the step case. So let me just write that
and then those would give you, those would both give you like the algorithm that we're
hoping for, right? Like you can use the base case to prove that the property holds for all leaves
and then you can combine all of these proofs using the step cases to go up the levels of the tree.
So now a bit more formally, the induction principle is let's just recall that for lists
the induction principle, instruction induction principle on lists was that if you prove it
for the empty list, if you can prove that empty property for the empty list and you can prove it
for any, if you have any, and if you prove it, if you can prove it that for any X
and Xs, if the property holds for Xs, so if you know that the property holds for Xs, then
you know that the property holds for the list made by Xs, X funds Xs. If you know those two
things, if you can prove those two things, then you can prove that the property holds for
any Xs, right? That was the induction principle for the tree, for the lists, for trees and for
nets, that was P of zero and show you that if for any n, sorry, if you have P of zero
and you can, if you can show that for any n, if you have that the property holds for n,
you can show, you can derive from that that the property holds for n plus one or suck n,
then the property holds for any n, right? So for trees, the induction principle is different,
it's, I mean, same but different. So if you can show that the property holds for a leaf
and if you can show that the property that for any, this time it's not just one,
like here we had just one Xs, one list and one number because every number is constructed in
terms of one number but for trees, we have every tree constructed in terms of two trees.
So for because of that, we can say that for any X, T1, T2, if you have the property holds for T1
and you have that the property holds for T2, then you can show that the property holds for
the node constructed by T1, X and T2. If you can show that, then you have that the property holds
for any tree. So it's basically the idea of mathematical induction on trees, right? So now
let's do an example of a proof using mathematical induction on trees.